Let's look at how you add waves.
Adding waves is called superposition.
Now if I had two crests hitting towards each other in a spring,
then when the two crests meet, they create a wave or something for a fraction of a second as they're passing through each other.
And they would create something that's bigger than both of them.
If this crest was five centimeters and this crest was four centimeters,
then when they meet, they would create a crest with an amplitude of nine centimeters.
We call this a super crest.
Very similarly, when two troughs meet, if this one was four centimeters and this one was five centimeters,
below the axis, then that would add up to nine centimeters below the axis.
So I'm going to give what I call a super trough.
The amazing thing about waves is when the two waves pass through each other,
they may create some new shape, but they actually pass right through each other unaffected.
And the way you could tell that is, if I'm standing there talking to someone and they're talking to me and we're speaking at the same time,
their sound wave travels through my sound wave.
And when their sound wave gets to me, it sounds like them and I can hear what they're saying.
And my sound wave travels through their sound wave and when it gets to them, they can understand what I'm saying.
If the two waves mix and then create a new wave that change the properties of each individual wave,
then when two people are talking to each other, it would get all garbled up.
Also, radio waves do the same thing.
Two radio waves can be passing by in here and I can tune in one radio wave or the other,
even though they're passing through each other.
When it comes to waves and adding them,
sometimes we get waves like this, like the square wave and the sort of triangular looking wave.
We want to add those two up.
We use the same idea of adding the amplitudes to find out what's going to happen.
So I can make a quick sketch and say there's the square wave and there's the triangular wave.
Let's see what happens.
So look at the beginning.
The square wave is five centimeters tall.
The triangular wave is zero.
So my first point would be five.
Then I go over here.
I might have the rectangular wave.
The square wave is five and the triangle is one.
So that's six.
If I work my way along the whole thing doing that, I'll end up with a wave like this.
So when these two waves meet, I might get a shape that looks like that.
It can be a lot more complicated when you have waves like this.
In order to find out what the result is when this wave and this wave are meeting each other,
I have to do the same thing.
I add up the amplitudes, but here it's so much busier.
I have to do one piece at a time.
I have to start over here and say zero plus zero is zero.
This wave is three high.
This wave is one below.
So three up, one down is two.
So I put a dot at two.
And you literally have to work your way all the way through this.
Going one on one space at a time and figuring out what it's going to be.
In the end, you'll end up with some weird wave that might look a little odd,
but that's what's going to happen.
That looks a little bit like what you see in a sound wave.
When you look on a oscilloscope, you see this very complex looking wave.
That complex looking wave is actually made up of all the simple waves put together.
And computers are really good at taking this complex wave and distilling it down to the simple waves.
We can find out what waves went into making that up.